Guide to the Annie Burr Lewis Papers
The Lewis Walpole Library
Annie Burr Lewis Papers
1849-1960
1915-1959
LWL MSS 21
The Lewis Walpole Library
35.6
58 boxes + 1 broadside
The collection contains correspondence, personal and family papers, and financial records that document the life, interests, and work of the American philanthropist Annie Burr Auchincloss Lewis (1902-1959).
Lewis, Annie Burr Auchincloss, 1902-1959
Glidden, Anna Dale Biddle Burgess, 1902-1984
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis (Yale 1918), 1979.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1900-1959 II. Personal Papers, 1902-1958. III. Family Papers, 1849-1955. IV. Financial Records, 1926--1959. V. American Red Cross Records, 1941-1946.
Annie Burr Lewis (1902-1959)
Annie Burr Auchincloss Lewis was born in Newport, Rhode Island, on July 22, 1902, the daughter of Emma Jennings Auchincloss and Hugh Dudley Auchincloss. She attended Miss Porter's School in Farmington, Connecticut, and married Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis in New York in 1928. She died in Hartford, Connecticut, on May 9, 1959.
Related Materials
Associated Material: Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20). The Lewis Walpole Library.
Associated Material: Annie Burr Lewis and Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Photographs (LWL MSS 22). The Lewis Walpole Library.
Associated Material: Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR), Connecticut Division Financial Records (LWL MSS 24). The Lewis Walpole Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, personal and family papers, and financial records that document the life, interests, and work of the American philanthropist Annie Burr Lewis (1902-1959). The correspondence is with her mother Emma Brewster Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942), her aunt Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939), and nieces, nephews, and cousins in the Auchincloss and Jennings family, as well as her friends from childhood, school, and adult life. Personal papers include her appointment books, awards, recipe books, school notebooks, scrapbooks and postcard albums, and family papers consist of genealogical materials documenting branches of the Auchincloss and Jennings families. Her financial records cover both her personal banking and investments. The last series holds records from Annie Lewis's service with the American Red Cross as assistant director for Volunteer Special Services (1941-1944) and Volunteer Field Representative for Camp and Hospital Service (1944-1946) in Connecticut.
Family papers also include materials related to the lives and estates of Emma Jennings Auchincloss and Annie Burr Jennings, plus a group of letters to Jennings from William Howard Taft, and inscribed portrait photographs of Taft and Benito Mussolini.
Separated Materials
Printed material found with the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching the library's online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Cooking, American; Women philanthropists; Diaries; Genealogical tables -- United States -- 20th Century; Portrait photographs; Photograph albums; Postcard albums; Recipes; Auchincloss, Emma Brewster Jennings, 1861-1942; Burgess, W. Starling (William Starling), 1878-1947; Chamberlain, Samuel, 1895-1975; Frissell, Varick, 1903-1931; Harkins, Emma Anita Nash, 1922-2011; Harlan, John M. (John Marshall), 1899-1971; Hudson, Elizabeth; Hurlburt, Mabel S.; Jennings, Annie Burr, 1855-1939; Kammerer, Olivia Heminway, 1892-1959; Kimball, Josephine Dodge, 1903-1981; Leonard, Joseph, 1877-1964; Lewis, Annie Burr Auchincloss, 1902-1959; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979; Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945 -- Portraits; Nash, Ruth Prentice Coffin, 1921-2007; Nash, Edmund Witherell, 1918-2004; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930 -- Portraits; First Congregational Church (Farmington, Conn.); Miss Porter's School (Farmington, Conn.); Mount Vernon Ladies' Association of the Union; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1900–1960; Series I; 10.56; 15 boxes
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Family, Friends and Colleagues, and Service and Affiliations.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence that had been kept separate from the enormous quantity of correspondence received by Wilmarth and Annie Lewis that now forms Series I in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20). Most of the letters here were addressed solely to Annie Lewis by members of the Auchincloss and Jennings family, her personal friends, and staff at organizations with which she was involved as a volunteer or donor. It is unclear who made the separation of these materials, but in their isolation they do set facets of Annie Lewis's life apart from the panorama of the Lewises' social and academic connections and activities.
  The Family Correspondence subseries holds letters from Annie Lewis's Auchincloss and Jennings siblings, aunt, cousins, and their children, and correspondence with her mother Emma Brewster Auchincloss (1861-1942) and favorite aunt Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939). Though she was very generous to, and interested in, all of her nieces, nephews, and their children, Annie Lewis developed closer relationships with Edmund, Emma Anita, and John Nash, the children of her sister Esther (1895-1986) and her first husband Edmund W. Nash (1896-1947). The three spent their childhood in the New York area prior to moving to Reno, Nevada, in 1929 for Esther Nash's divorce, and remaining in the West after she married Norman Biltz (1902-1973) in 1930. Also filed here are six folders of letters sent between Annie Lewis and her husband, most written while he was away on travels or she was in Virginia attending business meetings at Mount Vernon. There is one letter present from Wilmarth Lewis's brother George describing the camera equipment he had sent her; all other communications with the Lewis family are filed in Series I of Wilmarth Lewis's papers (LWL MSS 20).
  The second subseries, Friends and Colleagues, holds letters from former Farmington schoolmates and a group of suitors Annie Lewis had attracted in the early and mid-1920s. Among the latter were the explorer Varick Frissell (Yale 1926) who wrote from the snowy Grenfell Mission in Labrador, and Walter Rumsey Marvin (Yale 1922), who signed his ardent poetic tributes "Rummy" and wisely chose a career path away from creative writing. Her schoolmates included the thrice-married adventurer Anna Hope Dale Biddle Burgess Glidden (1902-1984), known as "Nannie," whose more than fifty letters to Annie Lewis narrate the second half of her peripatetic life. She left her husband and children in suburban Philadelphia for the charismatic naval designer W. Starling Burgess, and when that marriage foundered, Burgess left her scrambling to support herself through a series of jobs that included day labor on a farm, "slinging six lb pans" of frozen food in a New Jersey factory, selling skin care products on commission for Beauty Counselors Inc., and organizing a wool weavers cooperative in rural Maine. The letters in Series I show that Nannie, though resouceful, was just one of several friends—and family members—to whom Annie Lewis regularly provided seemingly unflagging moral, material, and financial support. As Nannie wrote to Wilmarth Lewis in 1976, "despite how different we were she always seemed to understand, which was more than most did." Letters from Starling Burgess explain the engineering projects for which he too sought backing, as do those from Olivia Heminway Kammerer whose school in Florence exposed young American women to Italian art and culture. Annie Lewis also supported many tradesmen, and filed here are correspondence and photographs from the paintings conservator Morton Bradley and furniture makers/restorers of the Nathan Margolis Shop, both concerning art and antiques she owned.
  The third subseries, Services and Affiliations, holds correspondence with organizations and institutions with which Annie Lewis worked over her lifetime. Prominent among these is the First Church of Christ, Congregational, in Farmington, and the files contain documentation of the several committees on which she served. Perhaps her most significant contribution was to the Restoration Committee which undertook a six-year project to raise and return the pulpit and sounding-board to their original location on the east wall; its success is marked by a plaque on the church wall acknowledging her effort. Annie Lewis's devotion to the Mount Vernon Ladies' Association of the Union was inspired by that of her aunt Annie Burr Jennings, who served as the third Vice Regent for Connecticut from 1915 to her death in 1939. Yale University was the focus of Annie Lewis's greatest philanthropic efforts through her establishment of Special Fund "L," the Annie Burr Lewis Fund, and the Lewis-Farmington Trust. Because the funds continued and were monitored long after her death by her husband, the existing records are in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20), Series VII, Boxes 324-325. However, filed here is documentation of Annie Lewis's work with the university's Medical Affairs Committee, School of Nursing, and Yale University Art Gallery, as well as the records of her extensive involvement with the Faculty Committee for Receiving Oxford and Cambridge University Children during World War II. Included there is a painted bowl that was a gift from of one of the young refugees whose family Annie Lewis sponsored during their stay in Farmington.
  Readers seeking to explore Annie Burr Lewis's network of friends and colleagues must also check the extensive correspondence files in Series I of the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20), as no attempt was made to remove from that collection letters addressed only to her.
  - Family
    - Auchincloss, Emma Brewster Jennings, 1915, 1933–1942 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
      Biographical / Historical
      Emma Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942), the mother of Annie Burr Lewis, married Hugh Dudley Auchincloss (1858-1913) in 1891. Papers related to her life, interests, and estate are filed in Series III. Family Papers.
    - Auchincloss, Hugh Dudley, 1920–1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Hugh Dudley Auchincloss Jr. (1897-1976) was the brother of Annie Lewis, and like her, a summer resident at Hammersmith Farm in Newport, Rhode Island. Auchincloss was also a financial investments manager for the Lewises, so additional correspondence with him can be found in Series IV, Financial Records.
    - Auchincloss, Hugh ("Yusha") D. Jr. and Alice, 1949–1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Hugh Dudley ("Yusha") Auchincloss III (1927-2015) was the son of Annie Lewis's brother Hugh D. Auchincloss (1897-1976) and his first wife Maria Nikolayevna Chrapovitsky (1899-1990).
    - Auchincloss, general, 1952–1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Auchincloss family birthday card for Annie Lewis, drawn by Jacqueline Bouvier, 1946 July 22 (Box Box 60, Folder 1)
      The celebrants saluting "Aunt Abie" in this birthday greeting are the children of Hugh and Janet Auchincloss, and were identified in a pencil inscription by Wilmarth Lewis; his notations on the verso assign authorship and a date of July 22, 1946. A sketch on the verso shows the couple's standard poodles presenting a birthday cake to Wilmarth and Annie Burr Lewis, aunt and uncle of the artist, whose enthusiasm for Walpole is humorously alluded to with a sign at the foot of the bed that reads "Horace Walpole Slept Here."
      The card is framed.
    - Biltz, Esther Auchincloss and Norman, 1943–1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Also contains letters from other members of the Biltz family.
    - Coe, Eunice ("Dunie") Jennings, 1900, 1913, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Contains clippings concerning Sarah Porter, the founder of Miss Porter's School, and her school's centenary celebration.
    - Collard, Ruth Auchincloss, 1944, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Dodge, Arthur Murray, 1952–1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Arthur Murray Dodge (1913-1974) was the first husband of Anita Nash, and the brother of Annie Lewis's close friend Josephine Dodge Kimball.
    - Dodge family, 1954–1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      The folder primarily holds letters and drawings from the children of Anita and Arthur Dodge; also present is a photostat of a draft letter written in 1955 from Annie Lewis to Annie Burr Auchincloss Dodge on the topic of their namesake Annie Burr Jennings.
    - Harkins, Emma Anita ("Buddy") Nash Dodge, 1952–1958 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
      Emma Anita Nash (1922-2011), known to the family as "Buddy," was the eldest daughter of Annie Lewis's sister Esther Auchincloss and a favorite niece.
      The folder also holds correspondence with psychiatrist Dr. John A. P. Millet regarding his work with Anita Dodge between the dissolution of her marriage to Arthur Dodge and her wedding to the author Philip Harkins (1914-1997).
    - James, Oliver, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jennings, Annie Burr, 1931–1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939) was the aunt of Annie Lewis. Papers related to her life, interests, and estate are filed in Series III. Family Papers. In addition, many of the postcards found in the albums in Series II, Personal Papers, were sent by Annie Jennings during her European travels.
      Includes a letter from Luke Lockwood to Annie Lewis.
    - Jennings, Oliver Burr, 1926–1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lewis, George W., 1946 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Lewis, Wilmarth Sheldon, 1926–1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-15)
      Includes one letter from the Lewises' friend Moreau Delano, dated December 11, 1927.
    - Nash, Edmund Burr, 1953–1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Nash, Edmund ("Ted") W., Jr., and Ruth Coffin, 1941–1959 (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
      Edmund W. Nash Jr. (1918-2004), the first-born of Annie Lewis's several nephews and nieces, was son of her sister Esther Auchincloss Nash. He married Ruth Prentice Coffin (1921-2007) in 1941; an artist, she was the daughter of Dorothy Prentice and Henry Sloan Coffin, president of Union Theological Seminary in New York. Nash served in North Africa and Italy with the United States Army during World War II. Though they lived in California, the Nashes remained close to the Lewises and would often spend time at "The Castle" in Newport.
    - Nash, Ruth Coffin: "The Tree Game", 1952 October 12 (Box 52 (Oversize), Folder 1-9)
      Leaf specimens collected in Newport and arranged by Ruth Coffin Nash. Also present is an undated hand-lettered label for "The Nash Beach-Glass Collection," likely from a display left behind after the family had visited.
    - Nash, Ruth Coffin: illustrated poems, undated (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 1-2)
      The two narrative poems written and illustrated by Ruth Nash were likely created as notes of appreciation after the Nash family had visited the Lewises.
    - Nash, Ruth Coffin: photostats of ink sketches, 1943–1945 (Box 53 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      Formerly in a brown paper wrapper inscribed by Annie Lewis: "RPN's drawings / Ruth Prentice Nash (Mrs. E. W. Nash) photostats of drawings sent E.W.N. when he was in Italy during the war, 1943-45."
    - Nash, John Francis, and Mary, 1941–1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      John Nash (1921-2008) was the son of Esther and Edmund Nash, and raised his own family in the West.
  - Friends and Colleagues
    - Acheson, Alice and Dean, 1945–1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Atherton, Ray and Maude, 1958–1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Bayne-Jones, Nannie Moore, 1958–1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Bradley, Morton C., Jr. (Morton Clark), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Brayton, Alice, 1919, 1949–1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      The folder also contains a 1954 letter to Annie Lewis from Catherine Auchincloss, enclosing a Newport-related letter to her from her cousin William A. Paton, dated November 15, 1919, which Lewis had sent on to Alice Brayton, and Brayton then returned.
    - Burgess, W. Starling (William Starling), 1939–1943 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Chamberlain, Samuel, 1935 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 2, Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      In his letter Chamberlain agrees to take photographs of the interior and exterior of the Cowles House, the Lewises's home in Farmington, which he would have printed as "contact postcards" in Boston. The resulting negatives are in Series V of the Lewises' photograph collection (LWL MSS 22), Box 10, folder 3, and two sets of postcards are in Wilmarth Lewis's papers (LWL MSS 20), Box 33, folder 8, and Box 277, folder 2.
      Also present here is a brochure advertising Chamberlain's "The American Scene" postcard series published by the Yale University Press, four printed postcards including a view of the Cowles House, and an uncut sheet of postcards.
    - Cogswell, Amy L., 1935 November 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dana, Katherine S., 1951–1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Foy, Isabelle, 1920, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Frame, Florence, 1943–1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Frissell, Varick, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Also present is a snapshot photograph of Annie Lewis that Frissell enclosed in one of his letters.
    - Glidden, Anna ("Nannie") Dale Biddle Burgess, 1940–1956 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Grummon, Louise Truslow, 1948–1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Harlan, John M. (John Marshall), 1926–1955 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Henry, Snowden, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Hudson, Elizabeth, 1958–1959 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Includes letters from Annie Burr Lewis to Hudson, and one to Hudson from Andre Mankowsky.
    - Hurlburt, Mabel S., 1950–1954 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Filed here is correspondence documenting Mabel Hurlburt's work to create an historical census of Farmington homes and properties, a project underwritten by Annie Lewis. The resulting card file, which was typed by Annie Lewis from Mabel Hurlbut's notes, is held by the Farmington Public Library. The cards, along with later survey worksheets, house photographs and other notes, are accessible through the library's website (http://farmingtonlibraries.org/farmington-homes/).
    - Kammerer, Olivia Heminway, 1940–1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Kennedy, John Drummond, 1926–1927 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Kimball, Josephine Dodge, 1927–1959 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Langan, John, 1943–1944 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Leonard, Joseph, 1949–1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Father Joseph Leonard CM (1877-1964) was an Irish priest in the Catholic Vincentian Order who taught at St. Mary's College, a teacher training school run by the Vincentian order at Strawberry Hill in Twickenham. Leonard befriended the Lewises in the early 1930s, and their relationship continued after he returned to Ireland in 1939, to join the Vincentian seminary at All Hallows in Drumcondra, Dublin. Additional correspondence with him can be found in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20).
    - Mahan, Ludlow, 1911 March 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      The item here is a letter sent by Annie Burr Lewis while on a trip to Egypt.
    - Marvin, Walter Rumsey, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Nash, Ogden, 1925 June 25 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Nathan Margolis Shop, 1939–1940 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      The Margolis Shop in Hartford specialized in the restoration of antique pieces and made reproduction furniture for clients including the Lewises.
      The file contains documentation of the Thomas Clark writing table and other furniture pieces.
    - Neave, Alexander Caldwell, 1924–1926 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Neill, Terence, 1926, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Terence Neill was the son of Katherine Livingston and Samuel Montaudevert Neill of New York; his grandfather, Edward M. Neill, had a summer home in Newport. An actor, Neill wrote just before his starring role with Bela Lugosi in the first American performance of Dracula.
    - Niesigh, Alys M. M., 1948–1955 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Parsons, John Caldwell, 1921–1922 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Scott, Ernest, 1950–1951 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Shepherd, Murtha and Merritt, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Documents regarding a study of traffic on Main Street, Farmington.
    - Stillman, Ruth, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Correspondence regarding their friend Elizabeth Hudson.
    - Talmadge, Prentice, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Vanderbilt, William Henry, III, 1917, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified
      - "Nogi", 1922 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "Phil," Princeton student, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - "Walter," Harvard student, 1920–1921 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Other friends, 1921–1958 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Engagement letters, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Engagement telegrams, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Wedding telegrams, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Other letters, 1923–1958 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
      The folders contain correspondence related to business, including letters from various vendors.
  - Service and Affiliations
    - Antiquarian & Landmarks Society, Inc. of Connecticut, 1957–1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Farmington Historical Society, 1954–1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - First Church of Christ Congregational (Farmington)
      - General correspondence and ephemera, 1900, 1947–1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Building Committee, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Church Committee, 1951–1954 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Landscape (Planting) Committee, 1952–1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        Includes correspondence with Christopher Tunnard.
      - Restoration Committee, 1950–1959 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Harold King photographs of church, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - "View from the North / The Meeting House and Church School", 1952 (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 3)
        Birds-eye view of proposed addition to First Church by William and Jeffrey Platt, New York; rendering by Schell Lewis; graphite on paper mounted on pulp board.
      - Restoration Committee financial, 1952–1959 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Hill-Stead Museum, 1946–1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Includes a copy of Theodate Pope Riddle's will.
    - Hroswitha Club, 1944–1957 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      The Hroswitha Club was an organization of women book collectors.
    - Miss Porter's School
      - Correspondence and reports, 1941–1958 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Historical material and photographs, 1902–1913 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        Most of the material is related to the 1913 centennial celebrations.
    - Mount Vernon Ladies' Association of the Union
      Annie Lewis became Vice Regent for Connecticut in 1942; her certificate of appointment is in Series II (Box 54, folder 3). The files here hold correspondence with Rosamund Beirne and others, including outgoing letters that were returned to Wilmarth Lewis after Annie Lewis's death in 1959. The bulk of the material is comprised of various unpublished reports on the furnishings, gardens, and history of restorations at Mount Vernon.
      - Correspondence and photographs, 1943–1959 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
      - Interview transcript, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
        A typed transcript, with carbon copy, of an interview with Annie Lewis broadcast on Hartford radio station WTIC (Travelers Broadcasting Service), February 15, 1954.
      - Reports, 1940–1951 (Box 8, Folder 6-13)
      - Reports, 1952–1958 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
    - National Council for Historic Sites and Buildings, 1952–1959 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Annie Lewis was a member of the National Council for Zone 1 (New England).
    - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 1952–1956 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Preservation Society of Newport County, 1950–1954 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Tercentenary Commission of the State of Connecticut, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Yale University
      - Committee on Medical Affairs, 1948–1954 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Committee on Medical Affairs, 1948–1954 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)